RYAN MOHRMAN

rmohrman@me.com

rvanmohrman.com

(720) 468-0234

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Technical innovator and thought leader

Iniquely talented software engineer with a broad range of experience commercializing sophisticated application software for the energy industry. Experience includes code development, cross-functional product team management, and solutions architecture. Effective working with the technical staff, marketing, sales, services, and users to define features and functions to ensure market success.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

PROFICIENT: Ruby, Rails, Python, Flask, VS Code, HTML5, CSS3, SASS, Bootstrap 3/4, Nginx, Heroku, DigitalOcean, SQL(MSSQL, Oracle SQL, Sqlite3, PostgreSQL), Javascript, jQuery, Version Control (git)

FAMILIAR: node is, React, D3 is, Swift, C#, AWS, Google Cloud, Azure, Unity

OPERATING SYSTEMS: Windows, Mac OS, Linux

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

ACTENUM CORPORATION, DENVER, COLORADO

2018 - PRESENT

A leading developer of schedule optimization software for the upstream gas and oil industry.

Product Manager

Hired to develop a disciplined, market-focused product development process and roadmap for new products. Included the voice of the customer into the product development process and transitioned development to a product vs. tools and services focus. Serve as a single point of contact within the company for product-related issues. Reported to the VP of Product Development.

• Introduced development team to product concepts, agile development rituals, and release process, resulting in the general availability of Upstream, Version 6.6 on October 30, 2019

AUCERNA F.K.A. ENERGY NAVIGATOR, HOUSTON, TEXAS

2013 - 2018

The energy industry's leading provider of solutions for integrated planning, execution, and reserves.

Senior Solutions Architect Denver, CO (2017 – 2018)

The needs of potential clients to design and develop workflows and present optimal solutions. Served as a trusted client advisor on product direction and migration from the current solution to future integrated product platform. Mentored other Solutions Architects, Product Owners, and customers on best practices and product features. Reported to the EVP of the US and Latin America.

- Led a DevOps initiative to build a sales demo and engineering test tool, and personally developed the integration automation tools and the SQL server and application server configurations
- Wrote a data integration tool to easily share data and workflows with the production forecasting and planning teams
- Prepared and delivered forecasting lectures (3 hours) for students at the University of Houston, Texas
 A&M, Colorado School of Mines, and provided certifications for extended education credits (30 50
 students per lecture).

US Product Manager, Houston, TX (2015 – 2017)

Reporting to the President and EVP of Engineering responsible for the Energy Navigator Products, AFE Nav, and Val Nav for the U.S. market. Worked directly with the Director of Marketing to update copy, and positioning of our products for US market.

- Built competitive landscape for both products in the US and worked with Sales and Marketing to develop targeted strategies to replace the incumbent competing application
- Prepared knowledge sharing sessions (lunch and learns), and delivered new content and workshops both internally to team and externally to customers

- Built prototype models and sample calculations to ensure the alignment of the product direction and roadmap with client requirements
- Defined epics and organized product development priorities to increase potential market penetration in the US

<u>Technical Sales/Services Engineer & IT Associate</u>, Houston, TX (2013 – 2017)

Reported to the VP, US Operations, and President, consulted with clients to understand where reserves estimation and reporting workflows could be improved. Developed best practices for production forecasting, reporting and reserves database management, and security.

- Led the largest implementation in US company history, consolidating 140 separate databases into a single source of information, reducing the reserves process to hours vs. weeks
- Doubled sales of Value Navigator YoY for 3 years, increasing contribution revenue from 5% to 40%
- Secured 2 of the top 3 largest clients in US company history by facilitating unparalleled demonstrations and consultations
- Redefined sales process, demo process, and implementation for Val Nav product to shorten the cycle time from kickoff to go-live and enable more refined success metrics

ENERPACT, HOUSTON, TX

2012 - 2013

Developer of enterprise decision support software for the Energy Exploration and Production industry.

Senior Software Engineer/Product Manager

Product managed, budgeted, scheduled, and planned system responsible for understanding client needs and communicating with the overseas development team to build, refine, and release features. Promptly resolved client questions and concerns and trained new clients on products as needed. Implemented source control and setup development practices. Wrote requirements and created proof of concepts for new features and solutions

HAROLD VANCE PETROLEUM ENGINEERING DEPARTMENT, COLLEGE STATION TX The petroleum engineering department at Texas A&M University.

Lead Web Developer / Web Developer Technician II

Responsible for upgrading and maintaining department website as well as working with professors to keep their web pages up and running. Supported IT by resolving all web-related issue tickets. Designed a full rewrite of the department's website to use Umbraco CRM utilized by the college of engineering. Administered web server and security for all websites and web apps within the department

REYNOLDS AND REYNOLDS COMPANY, COLLEGE STATION, TX

2009 - 2010

A leading developer of operations software for automotive retailers.

Application Developer

Employed full time while attending Texas A&M University. Worked on a team to move Standard Call from vb.net to c#.net as well as maintain any integrations and update child applications for the marketing and advertising tracking service

ATINUM E&P INC., HOUSTON TX

2008 - 2008

Oil and Gas Exploration Services.

Reservoir Engineering Intern

Analyzed production performance metrics and well files to update company reserves. Conducted field-level analysis and searched for workover, recompletion, and acquisition opportunities

EDUCATION & PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Texas A&M University, College Station, TX Bachelor of Science, Petroleum Engineering, Minor in Business

Scrum Alliance, Certified Scrum Product Owner

Pragmatic Marketing, Pragmatic Marketing PMC-III

ADDENDUM

RYAN MOHRMAN

These projects are being used to highlight my current skills and what I am capable of and specifically speaks to my ability to learn new things and apply them quickly to solve problems. For more details and additional projects please visit my website, ryanmohrman.com.

POWERUP GIFTING

A Ruby on Rails web app that will allow family and friends to share their gift registries for any event. This project started when my family dispersed across the country, and we wanted to maintain our tradition of gifting at Christmas. With a distributed and growing family, it became increasingly difficult to keep up with our changing interests. PowerUp Gifting is a central place that enables the family to create, share, and manage their gift registries.

Why not use an existing service?

It is well known that major players in the retail market have wishlist/registry applications. The largest of them, Amazon, have their way to create and share multiple lists with family, friends, or the public. PowerUp Gifting provides a more personal touch and has some key features that Amazon lacks.

- The ability to share items across lists for different events or audiences without duplication
- Gifts can be reserved by someone so that duplicates are not purchased
- Purchase sharing allows family members to pool money to buy larger gift items
- After a given event has occurred, the recipient of the gifts has a list of whom to thank for which gift (including different levels of anonymity for the purchaser)

Skills

- Requirements Gathering
- Full-Stack Web Development
- Application Design
- Product Management

Technologies

- HTML5/CSS3
- Bootstrap 4
- Light javascript/jquery extensions
- Rails version 5.2.3
- Ruby version 2.5.1
- Heroku
- GitHub

Considerations

- User Authentication and data security
- UI/UX Mobile-first design
- Mobile Development (future development) React Native to support iOS and Android
- OAuth 2.0 (future development) Adding Google, Facebook, Twitter, etc. as providers

SOUND STYLES

A Python and Flask web application that uses Spotify's web API to gather and show user data about their playlists. Working with a remote data scientist to provide him with backend and hosting support for his analytics. No previous experience working with Python, Flask, or Spotify's API. The goal here was to learn enough Python to help a data scientist with Python and Javascript skills build an application to highlight his project on the web. This project has sparked my interest in learning more Python and helping him with his portfolio site after finishing my own (project below).

Skills

- Remote Collaboration
- Backend Web Development
- API Design
- Project Management
- Rapid learning and application of new skills

Technologies

- HTML5/CSS3
- Bootstrap 4
- D3 javascript data visualization library (data scientist's lane)
- Flask version 1.1.1
- Python version 3.6.4
- Heroku
- GitHub
- VS Code with live share for collaborative development
- Spotify Web API

Considerations

- Spotify API Authentication
- UI/UX Responsive design
- Detailed documentation of backend for a Data scientist to take over if needed
- Python was required to help bring my skills closer to partners skills

FAMILY RECIPE MANAGER

A headless API to allow for secure storage and better utilization of family recipes. Nearly all recipes online today follow a similar structure that can be difficult to follow without printing out or reorganizing the recipe for a more usable format. This recipe manager breaks out all recipes into "stages" that reference a master ingredient list to help during the major phases of preparing and cooking. A recipe stage of "shopping" will display all required ingredients in a simple shopping list format, during the "prep" stage you will cover all necessary equipment and procedures required with the type and amount of ingredient at the time, and during the "cooking" stage(s) the type and amount of ingredients will be shown to quickly and easily identify how much of what to add when. The API has scale calculations as well as altitude adjustments and will be adding new features as the family uses it for our recipe sharing.

Skills

- Backend Web Development
- API Design
- Remote Collaboration (primary UI will be a React web app)
- Product Management (writing requirements for UI to be built by another developer)

Technologies

- Rails Verison 6.0
- Ruby Version 2.6.5
- React (version to be selected by front end developer)
- Nodeis
- Heroku
- Github
- VS Code

Considerations

- API is designed to be consumable by React and mobile applications
- Rails chosen for my familiarity, but separation from full Rails application allows front end developer to choose technology independently
- Some family that wants to share recipes also wants to continue using google docs (possible future integration)